Guide to the Ernst Cassirer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Essays and Lectures, 1893-1945; Series II; 7.5; (19 boxes)
  - Research notes
    - Miscellaneous (Envelope #203), n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1083)
    - Miscellaneous (Envelope #15), n.d. (Box 54, Folder 1083a)
- Correspondence, 1895-1958; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series III, Correspondence (Box 55) is divided into two subseries: Correspondence and Additional Correspondence. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Born, Max, 1937 (Box 55, Folder 1084)
    - Brunschvicg, Léon, 1937 (Box 55, Folder 1085)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1925-51 (Box 55, Folder 1086)
    - Gundolf, Friedrich, 1916-31 (Box 55, Folder 1087)
    - Heisenberg, Werner, 1937 Mar 24 (Box 55, Folder 1088)
    - Husserl, Edmund, 1937 Mar 11 (Box 55, Folder 1089)
    - Liebermann, Max, 1920 (Box 55, Folder 1090)
    - Mann, Thomas, 1939-40 (Box 55, Folder 1091)
    - Panofsky, Erwin, 1931 Jul 13 (Box 55, Folder 1092)
    - Schweitzer, Albert, 1934-58, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1093)
  - ADDITIONAL CORRESPONDENCE
    - Envelope #138
      - A. Ascher & Co., 1895 (Box 55, Folder 1094)
    - Envelope #176
      - Buchdruckerei Adolf Gertz, 1910 Jul 19 (Box 55, Folder 1095)
    - Envelope #89
      - Cassirer, Bruno, 1938 Jun 10 (Box 55, Folder 1096)
    - Envelope #138
      - Cassirer, Eduard, 1896 May 29 (Box 55, Folder 1097)
    - Envelope #40
      - Chang, Carsun, 1945 Mar 2 (Box 55, Folder 1098)
    - Envelope #117
      - Frischeisen-Köhler, Max, 1912 Dec 12 (Box 55, Folder 1099)
    - Envelope #8
      - Geoghegan, W. D., n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1100)
    - Envelope #27
      - Hafkesbrink, Hanna, 1944 Apr 24 (Box 55, Folder 1101)
    - Envelope #184
      - Margolius, Hans, 1929 (Box 55, Folder 1102)
    - Envelope #112
      - Petzäll, Åke, 1938 Apr 23 (Box 55, Folder 1103)
    - Envelope #91
      - [Trocker?], Herr, n.d. (Box 55, Folder 1104)
- Personal Papers, 1892-99; Series IV; 1; (2 boxes)
  Series IV, Personal Papers (Boxes 56-57), is divided into two subseries: Student Notebooks and Miscellaneous. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically.
  - STUDENT NOTEBOOKS
    - Envelope #138
      - Althochdeutsch/Gotisch, n.d (Box 56, Folder 1105)
    - Envelope #137
      - Brahm: Das deutsche Ritterdrama des 18ten Jahrhunderts; Anhang: Tendenzen der Sturm u. Drangperiode (Referat) (Box 56, Folder 1106)
    - Envelope #138
      - Cohen
        - Geschichte der neueren Philosophie, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1107)
        - Psychologie, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1108)
      - Natorp
        - Geschichte der alten Philosophie I. Winter Semester 1898/99 (Box 56, Folder 1109)
        - Geschichte der neueren Philosophie, n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1110-11)
    - Envelope #134
      - Natorp
        - Geschichte der neueren Philosophie III. Kant., n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1112)
    - Envelope #138
      - Natorp
        - Logik I., n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1113)
        - Logik II., n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1114)
        - Logik II., n.d. (Box 56, Folder 1115)
        - Pädagogik, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1116)
        - Pädagogik II., n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1117)
        - Die Philosophie Platons, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1118)
    - Envelope #137
      - Wundt
        - Psychologie I. Leipzig. Winter Semester 1892/93 (Box 57, Folder 1119)
        - Psychologie II., n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1120)
    - Envelope #138
      - Zur Lectüre. Vom 4 Juli 1894 bis ... [mostly concerning Fichte and Volkert], 1894-96 (Box 57, Folder 1121-25)
      - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1126)
  - MISCELLANEOUS
    - Envelope #183
      - Bibliography on various topics in unknown hand (Box 57, Folder 1127)
    - Envelope #138
      - Cassirer, Ernst: calling card with annotations, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1128)
    - Envelope #129
      - Cassirer Söhne: letterhead (Box 57, Folder 1129)
- Oversize, 1906-36; 3.5; (2 boxes)
  Oversize is composed of material from Series I, II, and IV. The papers are arranged in an order consistant with that in the original series.
  - PERSONAL PAPERS
    - Miscellaneous
      - Envelope #138
        - Storage box labeled "Alte Colleghefte" with illustration of Cassirer family company pasted on outside of lid. On inside of lid is pasted the printed name and address "Wloclaweker / Sulfit-Cellulose-Fabrik / J. & M. Cassirer / Berlin-Wloclawek" and also written the inscription "Unserem lieben Bruder und Socius Eduard zur freundlichen Erinnerung an gemeinsame Tätigkeit. Charlottenburg 16. Dezember 1913. Jaro Cassirer, Isidor Cassirer, Max Cassirer.", 1913 Dec 16 (Box 58, Folder 1130)
  - BOOKS
    - Das Erkenntnisproblem in der Philosophie
      - 1. Auflage, 1. Band, 2. Buch
        - Envelope #190
          - 1. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected(excerpts), ca. 1906 (Box 59, Folder 1131)
        - Envelope #193
          - 2. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected(excerpts), ca. 1906 (Box 59, Folder 1132)
          - 3. Kapitel: draft, holograph, corrected(excerpts), ca. 1906 (Box 59, Folder 1133)
    - Die Geschichte der antiken Philosophie
      - Erster Teil. Die Philosophie der Griechen von den Anfängen bis Platon von Ernst Cassirer
        - Envelope #189
          - III. "Die Eleaten": draft, holo- graph, corrected (excerpts) (Box 59, Folder 1134)
          - IV. "Die jüngere Naturphilosophie (Empedokles, Anaxagoras und die Atomistik): draft, holograph, corrected (excerpts) (Box 59, Folder 1135)
          - VII. "Platon": draft, holograph, corrected (excerpts) (Box 59, Folder 1136)
  - ESSAYS AND LECTURES
    Envelope #158
    - "Naturalistische und humanistische Begründung der Kulturphilosophie" [Wien]: draft, holograph, corrected (excerpts)
  - PERSONAL PAPERS
    - Miscellaneous
      - Envelope #186
        - Friedrich-Wilhelm-Universität (Berlin): announcement of inauguration of new rector, 1906 Oct 8 (Box 59, Folder 1138)
      - Envelope #146
        - Gawronsky, Dimitri, "Spenglersche Geschichtstheorie vor Sprengler," Neue Zürcher Zeitung, 1936 Jan 19 (Box 59, Folder 1139)
      - Envelope #120
        - Sample manuscript bundle wrapper (Box 59, Folder 1140)
      - Envelope #104
        - Das Unterhaltungsblatt, Berlin, 1926 Dec 8 (Box 59, Folder 1141)